<tool id="hierarchical-cluster-heatmap" name="Hierarchical Cluster Heatmap" version="0.0.1">
  <description> </description>
  <command interpreter="python">
    hierarchical-cluster-heatmap_amm2.py 
      --i $input1
      --d $design
      --o1 $out_file1
      --color_gradient $colorgradient
  </command>
  <inputs>
    <param format="tabular" name="input1" type="data" label="Select data" help="Dataset missing? See TIP below."/>
    <param format="tabular" name="design" type="data" label="Select design file" help="Dataset missing? See TIP below."/>
    <param name="colorgradient" size="30" type="text" value="jet" label="Optional - Input Color Gradient. See color options below."/>
  </inputs>
  <outputs>
    <data format="png" name="out_file1" />
  </outputs>
  <requirements>
    <requirement type="python-module">matplotlib</requirement>
    <requirement type="python-module">scipy</requirement>
  </requirements>
  <help>


.. class:: infomark

**TIP:** If your data is not TAB delimited, use *Edit Datasets-&gt;Convert characters*

-----

.. class:: infomark

**Color Options:** Jet, red_white_blue, spectral, red_black_sky, red_black_blue, red_black_green, yellow_black_blue, seismic, green_white_purple, and coolwarm

-----

.. class:: infomark

**What it does**

This tool Generates a Hierarchical Cluster Heatmap from a Side-By-Side dataset and a design file.
In the design file, samples must be called 'sampleID' and the sampleID classification variable should be called 'group'

-----

.. class:: warningmark

**Note**
This is port to galaxy of David Gladstone's:

### hierarchical_clustering.py
#Copyright 2005-2012 J. David Gladstone Institutes, San Francisco California
#Author Nathan Salomonis - nsalomonis@gmail.com

#Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy 
#of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"), to deal 
#in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights 
#to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell 
#copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is furnished 
#to do so, subject to the following conditions:

#THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, 
#INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A 
#PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT 
#HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION 
#OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE 
#SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.

  </help>
</tool>
