<tool id="lasso2" name="LASSO/Elastic Net Variable Selection," version="1.0.0">
    <description>Feature Selection using LASSO/Elastic Net.</description>
    <requirements>
        <requirement type="python-module">rpy2</requirement>
        <requirement type="python-module">pandas</requirement>
        <requirement type="python-module">numpy</requirement>

    </requirements>
    <stdio>
        <exit_code range="1:" level="warning" description="RuntimeWarning"/>
    </stdio>
    <command interpreter="python">
        lasso_enet_var_select.py
        --input $input
        --design $design
        --ID $uniqID
        --group $group
        --alpha $alpha
        --coefficients $coefficients
        --flags $flags
        --plots $plots
    </command>
    <inputs>
        <param name="input" type="data" format="tabular" label="Wide Dataset" help="Input dataset in wide format and tab separated. If file is not tab separated see TIP below."/>
        <param name="design" type="data" format="tabular" label="Design File" help="Design file tab separated. Note you need a 'sampleID' column. If not tab separated see TIP below."/>
        <param name="uniqID" type="text" size="30" value="" label="Unique Feature ID" help="Name of the column in your Wide Dataset that has unique Feature IDs."/>
        <param name="group" type="text" size="30" label="Group/Treatment." help="Name of the column in your Design File that contains group classifications."/>
        <param name="alpha" type="text" value=".5" size="30" label="α" help="Default .5"/>
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data format="tabular" name="coefficients" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string}: Coefficients"/>
        <data format="tabular" name="flags" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string}: Flags"/>
        <data format="pdf" name="plots" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string}: Plots"/>
    </outputs>
    <macros>
        <import>macros.xml</import>
    </macros>
<help>

@TIP_AND_WARNING@

**Tool Description**

The tool performs feature selection for each pairwise comparison of the levels of the group variable specified by user. The selection method is performed based on the logistic regression with Elastic Net penalty (with LASSO being a special case.) 

The penalty structure is controlled by α parameter (defined within [0;1] range) with the default value α = 0.5, that can be changed by the user. 
The value α = 1 corresponds to LASSO penalty with the strictest selection rule, while the value of the penalty α = 0 corresponds to ridge penalty which does not perform variable selection. 

Variable section is performed for all levels of α specified by the user in the range (0;1] with the value 1 corresponding the least number of variables and the most strict selection criterion (LASSO), while the value 0 corresponds only to the estimate shrinkage and no selection (ridge). 

The best subset of selected variables for a given α is selected by a cross validation procedure. 

More details about the Elastic Net and LASSO penalties can be found in the paper .

Zou, H., and Hastie, T. (2005). Regularization and variable selection via the elastic net. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (Statistical Methodology), 67(2), 301-320..

--------------------------------------------------------------------------------

**Note**

- This tool currently treats all variables as continuous numeric
  variables. Running the tool on categorical variables might result in
  incorrect results. 
- Rows containing non-numeric (or missing) data in any
  of the chosen columns will be skipped from the analysis.

--------------------------------------------------------------------------------

**Input**

    - Two input datasets are required.

@WIDE@

**NOTE:** The sample IDs must match the sample IDs in the Design File (below).
Extra columns will automatically be ignored.

@METADATA@

@UNIQID@

@GROUP@

**α**

    - Default .5

--------------------------------------------------------------------------------

**Output**

Three files are outputted.  The first TSV file contains the values of the coefficients (including zeroes) for each feature that were produced by the tool for each pair of comparisons (in columns.)  Those coefficients are produced for the transformed data (part of the LASSO/EN method) and should be interpreted with caution.  The second TSV file contains the corresponding flags for each feature with one (1) corresponding to selected features.  The feature is selected when the corresponding coefficient is not zero.  The third PDF file contains the pairs of graphs for each pairwise comparison between the groups.  For each pairwise comparison the first graph displays the behavior of the coefficients based on the value of the penalty and the shrinkage parameter.  The second graph provides the details of cross-validation procedure that is used for detection of the optimal penalty and for feature selection. 

</help>
</tool>
